<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Samsons seaven lockes of haire allegorically expounded, and compared to the seauen spirituall vertues, whereby we are able to ouercome our spirituall Philistims. By M. A. Symson, minister of the euangell at Dalkeith.</title>
            <author>Simson, Archibald, 1564-1628.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1621</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 71 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12262</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 22570</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102417</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838202</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838202</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2569</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12262)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2569)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1084:05)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Samsons seaven lockes of haire allegorically expounded, and compared to the seauen spirituall vertues, whereby we are able to ouercome our spirituall Philistims. By M. A. Symson, minister of the euangell at Dalkeith.</title>
                  <author>Simson, Archibald, 1564-1628.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 8-64 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>By Edward Raban, printer to the Vniversitie,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at Sainct-Andrewes :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1621.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Page 64 stained.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Virtues --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2569:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2569:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>SAMSONS SEAVEN LOCKES OF HAIRE: Allegorically expounded, and compared to the ſeauen Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Vertues, whereby we are able to ouercome our ſpirituall Philiſtims.</p>
            <p>By M. A. SYMSON, Miniſter of the Euangell at Dalkeith.</p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>stylized flower</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>Printed at Sainct-Andrewes, by <hi>Edward Raban, Printer to the Vniverſitie,</hi> 1621.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2569:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2569:2"/>
            <head>To the right Noble and <hi>ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Ladie, D. MARIE ARESKIN, Ladie Keith,</hi> Grace, Peace, and Happineſſe.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is the accuſtomable vſe of this fooliſh Age (MADAME) to claime Nobilitie vnto it ſelfe; drawing the Originall therof fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diuers Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains: ſome fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the diſcent of their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genitors, which the Poët ſcorned; not thinking that to belong to them which they themſelues did not atchieue: <hi>Nam genus, &amp; proavos, &amp; quae no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fecimus ipſi Vix ea noſtra voco.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Others, wiſer than theſe, affirmed that onlie Vertue did nobilitate; it beeing a gift of the minde, of more worth than anie fleſhlie prerogatiue: By which the ancient <hi>Romanes Lacedemonians,</hi> and <hi>Athenians,</hi> ſtudied to be famous thorow the world. But what were all theſe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2569:3"/>Cardinall Vertues? (though they could haue attained vnto the perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of them) but ſhining ſinnes, (as Sainct AVGVSTINE ſayeth) without CHRIST. For true Religion onlie perfecteth Nobilitie, and maketh men partakers of the Diuine Nature, which conſiſteth in the knowledge of the true God, and his worſhip, according to his will. This maketh <hi>Dauid,</hi> who ſprang of the baſe root of <hi>Ieſſe,</hi> more famous than <hi>Nebuchadnezar;</hi> &amp; <hi>Salomon</hi> to be prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Cyrus, Alexander,</hi> or <hi>Iulius Caeſar,</hi> euen till this day. And again, ſince God hath trained vp your Ladiſhip vnder the hand of a bleſſed Mother, that yee haue ſucked (with your Milke) the knowledge of the Trueth fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a Child, and growing in grace with your years, I wiſh that as your Lad. is borne noble by birth, and by your ſingular vertues become more noble; ſo by the ſincere profeſſion of the Trueth yee may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come moſt noble. Therfore I haue pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented theſe <hi>Seauen golden Lockes</hi> of Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall Vertues to be worne of your L. as Ornamentes (of more worth than
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:2569:3"/>brodered Gold or precious Pearls) vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the hid man of your heart: which will make you more beautifull in the eyes of Ieſus Chriſt, your ſpiritual Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, than if ye had all the glory of the worlde. Your ſpirituall <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> who creepe into Noble mens houſes, wil la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to rob you of your Ornamentes: therefore beware of <hi>Dalilah,</hi> and her en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſing ſpeaches; that yee may holde faſt the Trueth to the ende, which ye haue by hereditarie poſſeſſion; and I truſt ſhall deliuer it to your children. So be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeching God to multiplie all the gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of his Spirit vpon your Lad. with temporall felicitie, and hereafter heape vpon you the eternall weight of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, I reſt</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Ladiſhips ſeruant</hi> A. Symſon.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2569:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>BEcauſe (good Reader) thou haſt ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uourably accepted mine other two Lookes before, aſwell this laſt of <hi>The firſt ſeauen Dayes,</hi> as likewiſe the former vpon <hi>The ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen words</hi> which Chriſt ſpake on the Croſſe, euen at the accompliſhment of our Redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; therfore I am encouraged to preſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to thee this third <hi>Septenarie</hi> alſo, of <hi>Samſons ſeauen Lockes of Haire,</hi> mystically expounded of the ſeauen neceſſary Vertues, without the which none can be true Christians. And if ye reade the <hi>Fathers,</hi> how they allegorize both theſe &amp; all other parts of the old <hi>Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t,</hi> yee will not bee offended that I handle theſe <hi>Lockes</hi> by ſpirituall interpretation. Receiue this kindly, I pray thee, and by <hi>Gods</hi> helpe thou ſhalt haue <hi>The ſeauen Pſalmes of Repentance</hi> as ſoone as poſsiblie I may.</p>
            <p>Fare-well.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>A. SYMSON.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:2569:4"/>
            <head>ON THESE LOCKES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>LOckes,</hi> Ornament of Angels, Diadems</l>
               <l>Which the triumphing Quires aboue doe crowne:</l>
               <l>Rich Curles of Bountie, Pinnions of Renowne;</l>
               <l>Of that immortall Sunne immortall Beames.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Lockes,</hi> ſacred <hi>Lockes,</hi> no, adamantine Chaines;</l>
               <l>Which doe ſhut vp, and firme together binde</l>
               <l>Both that Contentment which in Life wee finde,</l>
               <l>And Bliſſe which with vnbodied Soules remaines.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Faire <hi>Locks,</hi> all <hi>Locks</hi> compar'd to you (though gold)</l>
               <l>Are <hi>Comets-Locks,</hi> portending Harme and Wrath;</l>
               <l>Or bauld <hi>Occaſions-Locke,</hi> that none can holde:</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Abaſaloms,</hi> which worke the Wearers death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>If hencefoorth Beautie e're my Minde ſubdue,</l>
               <l>It ſhall (deare <hi>Locks</hi>) be for what ſhines in you.</l>
            </lg>
            <bibl>
               <hi>W. D.</hi>
            </bibl>
         </div>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:2569:5"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>Iudg. chap. xvi. verſ. xix.</bibl> And ſhee made him ſleepe vpon her Knees: &amp; ſhe called a man, &amp; made him to ſhaue off the ſeauen Lockes of his head: and ſhee began to vexe him: and his ſtrength was gone from him, &amp;c.</q>
            </head>
            <p>THis Hiſtory of <hi>Samſon</hi> declareth vnto vs the infirmitie and weakneſſe of Gods chiefeſt Veſſels,<note place="margin">The in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmitie of Gods Sancts.</note> whenſoever they are left vnto themſelues: for albeit <hi>Samſon</hi> had both ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall and naturall ſtrength aboue others, yet when God leſt him but a little hee loſt them both, and became a pitifull prey &amp; ſpectacle to his enemies, whome before hee vanquiſhe. So this Hiſtorie is a faithfull Recorder, aſwell of the Vices as Vertues of the Sancts, &amp; a perfect mirrour wherin euery one may behold both the deformity &amp; beauty of his own perſon.<note place="margin">Simil. Iudg. 4.8. and 8.27. &amp; 11.39.</note> 
               <hi>Barac</hi> the Captain had his own faintheartednes, <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deon</hi> his Ephod, <hi>Iephtah</hi> his vnnaturall of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, &amp;c. Theſe things are manifeſt by the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:2569:5"/>Scriptures, and like Bekons ſet vpon the ſhore,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> to warne vs who ſeeme to ſtand, to take heede leſt wee fall. Yea, they are the Cicatrices, and marks of their woundes, to remember vs to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ware of the like ſnares of Satan.</p>
            <p>But although our ſpirituall enemies beguile vs, and enſnare vs in the groſſeſt ſinnes, yet let vs not deſpare: for there is ſtill mercy with God:<note place="margin">Prov. 24.16.</note> &amp; howbeit the Righteous may fall ſeven times aday, yet hee ſhall riſe againe. For ſure it is, that whom the Lord loveth, hee loveth to the ende: which we ſhall eaſily perceiue in this ſhort Treatiſe hereafter, God willing. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit the Lord externally chaſtiſe vs for our hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miliation, yet he taketh not his holy Spirit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs. For when he thought good he renewed his graces in <hi>Samſon,</hi> and as his haire grew, the Lord gaue him growth of ſtrength alſo: ſo that in his death hee became more victorious ouer Gods enemies than in all his life.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The grounds of doctrine.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="I"/> FIrst wee ſhall ſpeak, God willing, of the ſeauen <hi>Lockes</hi> of <hi>Samſons</hi> head,and the myſticall interpretation thereof.</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:2569:6"/>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="II"/> Next, of the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and the craftie deuiſe to ſuppriſe <hi>Samſon</hi> by <hi>Dalilah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="III"/> Th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>lie, <hi>Samſons</hi> facilitie in yeelding, and ſecuritie in ſleeping, being ouercome by his fleſhlie affections. Together with the juſt puniſhment thereof, in putting out of his eyes, which hee abuſed vnto his luſt. As alſo his captiuitie, and that ſhamefull ſpectacle which was made of him before the vncir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="IIII"/> And finallie, wee ſhall intreat of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons</hi> Triumph, the reſtitution of his ſtrength, and deſtruction of Gods enemies; repreſenting therein Christ Ieſus, our true <hi>Samſon,</hi> who by his death gaue the greateſt foyle to our enemies, and led captiuitie captiue.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:2569:6"/>
            <head>SAMSONS SEAVEN LOCKES OF <hi>HAIRE.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He number of ſeauen in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures is a Number of perfection;<note place="margin">The num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</note> as the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen Dayes, ſeauen Lampes, ſeauen An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels, ſeauen Viols, &amp;c. So vnder the ſeauen Lockes of SAMSONS Haire, which were the Markes of his NA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ZAREISME, are ſignified the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect Graces of the holie Spirit, which the LORD had beſtowed vpon him, and thorow which (as long as hee kept them) hee was more than a Conquerour.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:2569:7"/>
            <p>For albeit the Giftes of GODS holie Spirit bee innumerable, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finit, as Hee is himſelfe; yet there are ſome more principall, and moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie; <hi>(ſine quibus non)</hi> without the which none can perſwade-themſelues that the Spirit of GOD dwelleth in them,<note place="margin">Theſe gifts are abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutelie ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie.</note> nor yet that they ſhall inherite the Kingdome of Heauen. And theſe Seauen are ſo platted together, euen as SAMSONS LOCKES were, and as the links of a golden Chaine, that the one of them cannot bee without the reſt, and all of them cannot bee without one. And theſe are the Lockes which <hi>CHRIST</hi> prayſeth, in the fourth Chapter of the <hi>Canticles,</hi> at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning.</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:2569:7"/>
               <head>THE FIRST LOCKE. FAYTH.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt vvorke which the SPIRIT worketh in a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,<note place="margin">Fayth, the Mother of the rest.</note> is FAYTH; which is the Roote and Grandmother of all the reſt; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the which it is impoſſible to pleaſe GOD: and againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6.</note> heereby hee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth our Conſciences, that the Promiſes of Salvation (contained in the Worde of GOD) appertaine vnto vs, euen through CHRIST IESVS. Therefore, thoſe who are ignorant, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2569:8"/>doe not know theſe thinges, they haue not the Spirit:<note place="margin">Ignorance lacketh the firſt Locke.</note> Neyther yet thoſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who haue an Hiſtoricall Fayth, as the Deuils haue, and doe not applie theſe Promiſes vnto themſelues: they haue no part (I ſay) in this Buſineſſe, neither anie fellowſhip with the Spirit of Grace. For which cauſe wee ſhould moſt earneſtlie trie our ſelues, whether the Spirit of God bee in vs, (vnleſſe wee bee Reprobates;) and that eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciallie by Fayth; to wit, If wee knowe what are the Promiſes of Salvation; of the remiſſion of our ſinnes; of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our bodies; and of Life eternall. For albeit theſe thinges are not ſeene by the eye of naturall reaſon, and although fleſh and blood doeth not reveale it vnto vs; yet the Spirit of GOD worketh an aſſent and conſent in our mindes, vnto the trueth of them, and fullie perſwadeth vs thereof.</p>
               <p>But becauſe manie (alace) haue a vaine opinion of Fayth,<note place="margin">Three re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markable Notes to trie Fayth.</note> (and who is hee (of what Religion or Sect ſoever) that doth not boaſt himſelfe of Faith?) therefore (GOD willing) I ſhall giue
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2569:8"/>you three marks, by the which ye may diſcerne whether this bee a naturall Locke, growing out of SAMSONS owne head; or guilded and coloured, and falſe Haire, which neuer grew out of SAMSONS braine.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> By the groundes of the word.</note>The firſt marke whereby to diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſh true Fayth from that which is counterfet, is, by the ground thereof: for true Fayth groundeth her ſelfe on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vpon the word of GOD, and Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonicall Scriptures: for it is the word onelie which warrandeth the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: <hi>My Sheepe heare my voyce,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.4.</note> ſayeth our LORD: for if Angels, or men, would ſpeake Oracles vnto vs,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Act.</hi> 17.11</note> or <hi>Paul</hi> preach vnto vs, yet with the men of <hi>Berea</hi> wee muſt ſearch the Scriptures, and trie whether hee ſpeake according as it is written. And if an Angel ſhould preach a contrarie Doctrine,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Galat.</hi> 1.8.</note> we ſhould count him <hi>Anathema.</hi> Then wee muſt not build our Fayth vpon the Decrees of the Church, and belieue <hi>Fide impli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cita,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> faith. <hi>1</hi> Pet. <hi>3.15</hi>
                  </note> with an in-folded Fayth, or rather euill-folded Fayth. When the Apoſtle commandeth vs to giue a reaſon of our
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2569:9"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="19" facs="tcp:2569:9"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2569:10"/>Fayth to euerie one that asketh it, ſhall wee haue none other reaſon to render, but to wrap our ſelues in the Clouts of Ignorance? and ſay, wee belieue as the Church belieueth? For the men of <hi>Samaria</hi> anſwered to the woman of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maria</hi> farre better, ſaying, <hi>Now wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieue, not becauſe of thy ſaying, for wee haue heard him our ſelues,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iohn</hi> 4.42</note> 
                  <hi>and know that this is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the Christ, the Saviour of the worlde.</hi> Neyther ſhould our Fayth bee groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vpon the ſand of the Popes Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, his ridiculous <hi>Golden Legends,</hi> (which the Papiſts themſelues ſcorne) nor yet vpon the ancient Fathers, as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſayeth, <hi>Non quid dicit Donatus, aut Augustinus, ſed quid dicat DOMI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NVS:</hi> that is, Wee muſt not take heede what <hi>Augustine</hi> (that Divine Doctor) ſayeth, neither what <hi>Donatus</hi> (that damnable Hereticke) ſayeth; but what the LORD ſayeth in his holie Scriptures. And let vs holde faſt that which the Apoſtle Sainct <hi>Peter</hi> recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendeth vnto vs, ſaying, <hi>We haue alſo a more ſure word of the Prophets, whereunto ye doe well that yee take heede,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19</note> 
                  <hi>as vnto a light
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2569:10"/>that ſhineth in a darke place, vntill the day dawne, and the day-ſtarre ariſe in your hearts.</hi> For the worde of God is able to make that man of God abſolute,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.17.</note> being made perfect vnto al good works. Then true Fayth muſt altogether leane to the Scriptures, which onelie are ſufficient to leade vs vnto perfection.</p>
               <p>The next triall of our Fayth, is by the certaintie therof,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Heb.</hi> 11.1.</note> which th' Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, that is, A full perſwaſion of the certaintie of thoſe thinges which wee belieue: yea, an Euidence and demonſtration of thinges which are not ſeene: For what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thinges wee belieue, tranſcende and are aboue the reach of reaſon, or are flat contrarie to nature, ſenſe, and reaſon, which fleſh and blood cannot perſwade vs of, (as of the leaſt article of our Faith,) they muſt be reuealed to vs by our Father which is aboue. Now when I ſpeak of the certaintie, I meane not the quantitie; as though I did af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, that a weake Faith could debarre vs; but I craue a true Fayth, which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwadeth our conſciences of Gods fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2569:11"/>in Chriſt, and maketh vs ſay with Sainct <hi>Paul, I believed, and therefore did I ſpeake:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.13</note> and to ſay alſo with the Centurion,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Mark</hi> 9.24</note> 
                  <hi>I belieue, Lord, helpe my Fayth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third marke whereby this true Fayth is diſcerned,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Triall of their works.</note> is by the fruits ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: For it is not like the Figge Tree which was decked onelie with the greene Leaues of an outwarde ſhow, and yeelded no fruite vnto the LORD IESVS,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.19.</note> who hungered for it: But this true Fayth is like the Tree which groweth by the Rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 1.3.</note> and bringeth foorth fruite in due ſeaſon.</p>
               <p>This ſurelie verie greatlie condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth all theſe godleſſe Atheiſtes of our time, who brag of an ydle Fayth, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out anie care of a good life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:2569:11"/>
               <head>THE SECOND LOCKE. The loue of God.</head>
               <p>THE Spirit of GOD wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth not ſo ſoone Fayth in a Chriſtian heart, but likewiſe as ſoone hee ſheddeth abroad alſo the Loue of GOD in his ſoule: For as the Fire hath theſe two principall qualities, to wit, Light &amp; Heate;<note place="margin">Simil.</note> euen ſo hath the true knowledge of GOD the Loue of GOD conjoyned there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with. For how can wee loue the thing which wee know not? Yea, the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the Loue groweth according to the meaſure of the knowledge: For no man can loue the Pearle,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> vnleſſe hee know the validitie, vertue, and price of it; and then hee eſteemeth of it. Hee that loueth not the <hi>LORD IESVS</hi>
                  <pb n="24" facs="tcp:2569:12"/>let him bee accurſed. Hee asked three times at <hi>Peter,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.15</note> if hee loved him? not if hee knewe him; to declare, that the knowledge of GOD, without his loue, is vnprofitable.</p>
               <p>Trie the loue which you beare to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes <hi>GOD</hi> by theſe fiue markes: Firſt,<note place="margin">Fiue marks whereby to try our loue. <hi>1.</hi> Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall.</note> if it bee principall: and when yee compare other things (which ye loue) with him, trie which of them yee loue beſt. <hi>Hee that loveth Father, or Mother, or Wife, or Land, &amp;c. better than mee</hi> (ſayeth our Saviour) <hi>is not worthie of mee.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 10 37.</note> For he firſt loued vs: yea, hee loued vs more than all the other creatures, and tooke our fleſh vpon him, and died for vs: what ſhould wee then doe for him? But the ſwiniſh <hi>Gadalenes</hi> of this worlde loue their Swine better than him:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.34.</note> theſe rich Gluttons loue their Bellies better than him: and theſe co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous and earthlie minded men loue Mammon better than <hi>GOD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Next,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sincere.</hi>
                  </note> trie thy Loue by the ſinceritie thereof, and for what cauſe thou loueſt <hi>GOD;</hi> whether for his owne cauſe, and the ſweetneſſe which is in him; or
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:2569:12"/>for ſome temporall gaine and rewarde that thou lookeſt for at his handes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou loueſt him: If it bee for gaine, it is but mercenarie, and the loue of an Hyreling: But wee ought to loue the <hi>LORD</hi> as a chaſte woman doeth her Husband:<note place="margin">Simil.</note> not for his Riches and Honours, but for loue of himſelfe: yea, ſhee counteth it no burthen to begge with him. Euen ſo muſt wee loue the <hi>LORD</hi> for himſelfe, &amp; the goodneſſe which is in him: Yea, it is a part of mercenarie wages to loue <hi>GOD</hi> for eternall Life: but rather wee muſt loue eternall Life for him, that wee may bee with him; for without him eternall Life were eternall Death.</p>
               <p>Thirdlie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> The loue of GODS Houſe.</note> wee may trie the loue of <hi>GOD</hi> to bee true in vs, if wee finde in our ſelues that wee loue <hi>GOD</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and his Houſe.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 116.1</note> 
                  <hi>I loue the LORD dearlie</hi> (ſayth the Prophet <hi>David.</hi>) And, <hi>O LORD, I haue loued the Habitation of thine Houſe,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 26.8.</note> 
                  <hi>and the place where thine Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour dwelleth.</hi> And againe,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 27.4.</note> 
                  <hi>One thing haue I craued of the LORD, that I will re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>quire, That I may dwell in the Houſe of the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2569:13"/>LORD all the dayes of my life, to beholde the Beautie of the LORD, and to viſit his Temple.</hi> Reade the foureſcore &amp; eight <hi>Pſalme,</hi> which beginneth, <hi>O LORD of Hostes! how amiable are thy Tabernacles!</hi> and reade it vnto the ende, and yee ſhall perceiue howe well <hi>David</hi> loued the <hi>LORDES</hi> Houſe. Which ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſtlie argueth, that theſe vngodlie Atheiſtes, and faythleſſe Papiſtes, who refuſe <hi>GODS</hi> publicke Houſe, but at ſome ſuperſtitious times, haue no loue of <hi>GOD</hi> in their heartes.</p>
               <p>Farther, yee ſhall trie the loue of <hi>GOD</hi> which yee haue in your heart by the loue that you carrie towardes your Neighbours,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>4.</hi> The loue of the Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</note> the Brethren, and Members of <hi>CHRIST:</hi> For howe can yee loue the inviſible <hi>GOD,</hi> the Father,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4.20</note> whom yee ſee not, if yee loue not his Children whom yee ſee? <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> ſayeth that hee was a Companion vnto all them that feared the <hi>LORD:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.63.</note> as alſo hee hated all thoſe that hated the <hi>LORD.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And finallie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>5.</hi> The ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred of ſinne</note> if yee would trie whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther yee loue the <hi>LORD</hi> truelie, and
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:2569:13"/>whether or not yee haue the ſecond Locke of Haire on your head, then ſee how yee are affected towardes euerie ſinne:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Pſa.</hi> 97.10</note> For hee that loueth the <hi>LORD</hi> hateth all euill: So that of neceſſitie wee muſt hate all kinde of ſinnes, both in our ſelues, and in all others.</p>
               <p>And now by theſe markes yee may trie whether yee haue the true loue of <hi>GOD</hi> in your heartes, or not.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="part">
               <head>THE THIRD LOCKE. The feare of God.</head>
               <p>THIS may ſeeme ſtrange, that wee muſt both loue and feare <hi>GOD;</hi> when as the Apoſtle ſayeth,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 4, 18</note> that perfect Loue chaſeth away Feare. But ye muſt vnderſtand that there is both a ſlauiſh feare, and a childiſh feare: the Slaue fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:2569:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:2569:14"/> 
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:2569:15"/>for paine; the Childe out of loue feareth to offende:<note place="margin">Childiſh feare.</note> ſo that the greater loue there is, there is alſo the greater feare to offende him whome thou lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt.</p>
               <p>But becauſe men may deceiue them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues concerning this Feare of <hi>GOD,</hi> I ſhall heere (God willing) giue you a briefe Rule, which can verie hardlie <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ayle:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>NOTA.</hi> Bee af ayde to offende God in the ſmalleſt thoughts. Pro. <hi>28.14</hi>
                  </note> that is, <hi>If thou makest conſcience, and feareſt to offende GOD in the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thought of thine heart:</hi> For hee that is afrayd to offend in leſſer things, will he not be more loath to offend in grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter matters? as is ſayde, <hi>Bleſſed is hee that feareth continuallie.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But (alace) wee may ſay with <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> that <hi>the ſeare of GOD is not in this place.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 20.11.</note> For if the feare of <hi>GOD</hi> were in your heartes, it would bee a Bridle to reſtraine you from euerie euill, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoug there were neyther King, Law, nor Iuſtice. But if it bee an externall Feare which ſtayeth you from doing euill, then yee lacke the third Locke of <hi>Samſons</hi> Haire.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="part">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:2569:15"/>
               <head>THE FOVRTH LOCKE. Obedience to God.</head>
               <p>THIS Obedience to GOD is the firſt fruite of the former three: for <hi>Abrahams</hi> fayth was knowne by his obedience,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 12.4 <hi>and</hi> 22.16</note> in leaving his natiue Countrey, and ſacrificing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is ſonne. <hi>If yee loue mee,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioh.</hi> 14.21</note> ſayeth CHRIST, <hi>keepe my Commandementes.</hi> This Obedience is not onlie in doing,<note place="margin">Obedience actiue and paſsiue.</note> but alſo in ſuffering for him. As CHRIST was obedient to the death of the Croſſe, ſo wee muſt learne of him obediently to ſuffer for his Names ſake, whenſoeuer wee are called there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vnto.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22.</note> This obedience is better than Sacrifice: and diſobedience is like the ſinne of Witch-craft, and Idolatrie. But to trie thine Obedience, whether
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:2569:16"/>it bee true, yee ſhall marke theſe three thinges in it.<note place="margin">Markes of true obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience. <hi>1.</hi> Material pointes, and ſubſtantial. Mat. <hi>15.9</hi>
                  </note>
               </p>
               <p>Firſt, let vs beware, that in euery part of GODS worſhip, which is mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, wee haue a warrand out of his worde, or elſe wee worſhip GOD in vaine, following for Doctrine the Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions of men. If it bee circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall, as concerning Times, Places, Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiours, Habites, &amp;c. ſee that they be not againſt the materiall grounds, and that they import no ſuperſtition, nor profanitie; and then it is obedience. For hee that is not againſt vs, is with vs. But if they bee Idolatrous, Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious, or Scandalous, they ought not to bee obeyed, leſt wee ſhould obey Men rather than GOD.</p>
               <p>Next, that our obedience bee free, and without compulſion:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Free obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience.</note> For GOD loueth not coacted ſervice, but a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Sacrifice.</p>
               <p>And laſt, our obedience muſt bee in euerie thing:<note place="margin">3. <hi>Totall.</hi>
                  </note> that as the Centurion ſayde of his ſervantes, <hi>I ſay to one, Goe, and bee goeth: and to another, Come, and hee commeth,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 8.9.</note> &amp;c. ſo muſt wee, without
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:2569:16"/>reaſoning with fleſh and blood, ſimply obey GODS will in euerie thing.</p>
               <p>But becauſe wee are not able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect eyther the actiue or the paſſiue obedience of our ſelues, therefore our Sauiour CHRIST hath done well for vs, who hath perfectlie ſatisfied both the Law and GODS Iuſtice for our ſinnes, euen by his owne righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="part">
               <head>THE FIFTH LOCKE. Mortification of our luſts.</head>
               <p>THIS is the fifth neceſſarie gift of the holie Spirit, of the which th'Apoſtle ſaith,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Coloſ.</hi> 3.5.</note> 
                  <hi>Morti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie therefore your members which are vpon the earth: fornication, vncleanneſſe,</hi> &amp;c. And againe hee deſireth the <hi>Corinthians</hi> to <hi>keepe themſelues from all pollution of the
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:2569:17"/>fleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.1</note> And likewiſe hee willeth the <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latians, not to fulfill the deſires of their fleſh.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gal.</hi> 5.16.17.</note> And this is a continuall exerciſe: for ſo long as wee liue heere on earth our fleſh will ſtill rebell againſt the Spirit: therefore muſt we ſtriue continually to beate downe the corruptions of our vilde and wicked nature.</p>
               <p>Nowe the true triall of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is,<note place="margin">Triall of Mortifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</note> firſt if it bee vniverſall; leſt that yee reſiſt your fleſh in one affection, and yeelde vnto it in another. As if ye would refuſe Papiſtrie,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1.</hi> Vniver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall.</note> and imbrace Sacriledge;<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iudg.</hi> 15.15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16.4 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.9.</note> fight againſt the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and play the Harlot with <hi>Dalilah;</hi> kill the poore <hi>Agagits,</hi> and the leane Cat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tell, tell, and ſpare the King and his fatte Beaſtes aliue. So yee will entertaine a ſinne which is pleaſant, and profitable for you, and thinke to caſt off the reſt. No, no, make no diviſion, I beſeech you, in this ſlaughter of ſinne; but cut it whollie downe, and pull it vp by the rootes, that all its branches may periſh. Bee not onelie an enemie vnto one ſinne, but vnto all; leſt that one ſinne beeing left aliue, and nouriſhed
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:2569:17"/>without repentance, it openeth the doore vnto all the reſt.</p>
               <p>Next, if yee humble your bodie, and chaſtiſe your fleſh, without hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocriſie, and deſire of vaine glorie:<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2.</hi> Without hypocriſie.</note> without ſuperſtition, and without anie pryde, and a vaine opinion of me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite. For what will thy ſillie Suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringes, Pilgrimages, Faſtinges, and Abſtinences availe thee before GOD? for Hee delighteth not in the torture and tormenting of mens fleſh; ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther doeth His Kingdome conſiſt in Meate or Drinke: but Hee requireth of vs a perpetuall mortification, and ſanctification: and not that we ſhould take libertie to ſinne, vnder hope of Pardon, and thinke to acquite our ſelues by doing of Pennance. But let vs continuallie ſtudie to mortifie and ſubdue our vilde luſtes and affections, purting our whole truſt &amp; confidence in the mercies of GOD, and merites of CHRIST our Saviour.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="part">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:2569:18"/>
               <head>THE SIXTH LOCKE. Prayer and Prayſes.</head>
               <p>THE ſixth Locke is PRAYER and PRAY<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SES, which are the life of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion: for either we lacke ſome things for which wee muſt pray vnto God; or haue receiued ſome, for which wee ought to bee thankfull. So all our life time, that is, euery day, euery night, yea euerie houre and moment, wee muſt pray:<note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Pray continually,</hi> ſayth the Apoſtle. But our Prayer muſt not onlie bee ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball: for wordes ſerue more for men, than for God. Our Prayer muſt bee mentall:<note place="margin">Prayer mentall. Exod. <hi>32.10.</hi>
                  </note> as God is a Spirit, and heard <hi>Moſes</hi> crie, although hee vttered no words. Let vs not bind our ſelues vnto words, as manie doe: but as our neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie increaſeth, ſo let vs powre out our heart vnto God.<note place="margin">Reuerent in prayer.</note> But aboue all thinges let vs ſpeake reuerentlie vnto God, and
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:2569:18"/>conſider with what Majeſtie wee haue to doe: and as hee is the moſt excellent Majeſtie, ſo we ſhould dreſſe and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe our ſpeaches, and drawe in our wandering affections and cogitations, that our Prayers bee not turned into ſinne, and that hee caſt not backe the dongue of our ſacrifices vpon our fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: (for the Lord abhors the ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of fooles:) leſt our Prayer, which is the Key to open the Heauens, become a Barre to ſhut them vpon vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Pray in fayth.</note>Let vs pray alſo in faith, perſwading our ſelues that the Lord heareth vs, and will grant vs all thinges which are neceſſarie and expedient for vs. Let vs pray ardentlie and earneſtlie, not fain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in prayer,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Luke</hi> 18.5.</note> following the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate widow. Let vs not preſcribe times vnto him, nor grudge againſt him, li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miting the holie One of <hi>Iſrael:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">No pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of time.</note> but at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tende patiently his Majeſties good pleaſure: for hee is faythfull who hath promiſed. As alſo, let vs prayſe him chearfullie, and rejoyce in him with all Hymnes, and Pſalmes, and Spirituall Songs, with grace in our hearts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="part">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:2569:19"/>
               <head>THE SEVENTH LOCKE. Conſtancie to the ende.</head>
               <p>ALl theſe former graces of the Spirit are beginning and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companying graces;<note place="margin">Conſtancie a finiſhing grace.</note> but this gift of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtancie is a perfecting grace, crowning all the reſt: whervnto the Apoſtle manie times exhorteth the Churches,<note place="margin">2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.10</note> &amp; complaineth of the back ſliding of manie, with <hi>Demas,</hi> who im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braced this preſent world: of whom he ſpake weeping, that they were enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Phil.</hi> 3.18.</note> Our Sauiour ſayth, <hi>He that perſeuereth vnto the ende ſhal be ſaued:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth.</hi> 24 13.29</note> and it is propheſied, <hi>that thoſe who ſeemed to be ſtars, ſhall fall fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Heauen.</hi> Let vs therefore craue of God, <hi>Qui dat velle, &amp; perficere,</hi> who both giueth vs to will, and to perfect; that he may, (after we haue ſuffered a little,) make vs per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, confirme,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Peter</hi> 5.10</note> ſtrengthen, and eſtabliſh vs.</p>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:2569:19"/>
                  <head>The conſpiracie of the Princes of the Philiſtims, <hi>againſt Samſon.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WE haue heard alreadie the extraordinarie gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces &amp; ſtrength which was in <hi>Samſon:</hi> and now wee ſhall take a view alſo of the extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie temptations of his enemies, whereby they rob and ſpoyle him of the ſame: by the which we may learne, that the greater gifts of God men haue,<note place="margin">Greateſt gifts, grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</note> they ſhall looke for the greater tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. God hath not giuen vs Armour to rouſt, or hing or lie beſide vs; but that we ſhould vſe them. Therefore let no man brag in his gift: for when it is tried, our weakneſſe will be alſo tried.</p>
                  <p>Next, the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> were not able to withſtand <hi>Samſon</hi> by their ſtrength;<note place="margin">Satan pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailes more by policie than power.</note> but they circumuene him by their policie and craftie dealing. The Deuill is both a Lyon and a Serpent, yet he preuaileth
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:2569:20"/>more by his craftineſſe than by his crueltie. A Lyon is heard when he roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth afarre off, and is eſchewed: but a Serpent commeth creeping ſoftlie, and whiſtling, and poyſoneth vs craftily. O the deepneſſe of Satan! beware of him, and of his ſleights.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Geneſ.</hi> 3.1</note> He came not to <hi>Eua</hi> in the ſhape of a Lyon, but of a Serpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Therefore let vs take heed of the craf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie temptations of the Deuill, leſt hee deceiue vs by his ſubtilties. The firſt Church grew and increaſed vnder the ten bloodie Emperours, euen whileſt the Lyons roared, and deuoured her members: but when ſhe came to peace vnder <hi>Conſtantine, Conſtans,</hi> and <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius,</hi> then the Deuill poyſoned her with the damnable Hereſies of <hi>Arrius, Pela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gius,</hi> &amp; <hi>Donatus:</hi> ſo that the Church was more miſerably rent and conſumed by the craft and ſubtiltie of the Deuill.</p>
                  <p>We are alſo to pray to God, to keepe vs from the policie of <hi>Pharoah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.10 <hi>and</hi> 14.9.</note> (who ſaith, <hi>Let vs deale wiſely with the Iſraelites, and cunningly vndermine them</hi>) more to bee feared in his policies, than when hee came after the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> with his Horſes
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:2569:20"/>and Chariots. And the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uailed more againſt <hi>Samſon</hi> by the craft of <hi>Dalilah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.3.18</note> than by their Portes and Barres in <hi>Azza.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdlie, ye ſee that ſinne beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth a ſnare to the ſinner.<note place="margin">Sinne a ſnare to the ſinner.</note> 
                     <hi>Samſon</hi> was greatly addicted to his fleſhlie pleaſures, and they brought him to deſtruction. Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lots hunt for the precious ſoule of a man: yea, they are a Pit,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 6.26 <hi>and</hi> 22.14</note> wherinto man falleth, and cannot reſcue himſelfe. Let vs therefore mortifie our affections, &amp; giue no liberty to our fleſh, to fulfil the luſts thereof: for the baites of our plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures ſeeme delectable; but wee ſee not the hook which lieth vnder them:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 5.3.4</note> they ſeeme to bee Honey in our mouth, but they will be bitter as Wormwood, and ſharpe as a two-edged Sword.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Allegorie of the Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims and Dalilah.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>THE Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> doe viuely repreſent <hi>Beelzebub,</hi> and the reſt of the Princes of darkneſſe; &amp; <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lilah</hi> repreſenteth the fleſh, their aſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate, who confederate themſelues a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:2569:21"/>all thoſe whom they ſee marked with the graces of God, &amp; ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthened by his Spirit, to reſiſt and ouercome them: for wee haue not a fight with fleſh and blood, but againſt Spirituall wickedneſſes, and the Princes of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: and therefore, ſeeing we haue to doe with ſo potent enemies, who haue ſo many aduantages of vs; they being Spirituall,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and wee earthlie; they in the Aire, &amp; we on the Earth; they ſtrong, and we weake; they wiſe, and we foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh; they manie and wee fewe; &amp;c. ſhould wee not craue at God, that wee might, ſight a good Fight? and that he would furniſh vs with all Armour conuenient for that combate; and ſtrenghthen vs by his grace, that wee be not ouercome of our enemies?</p>
                  <p>The fitteſt inſtrument which the Deuill can find out to ſuppryſe a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,<note place="margin">Our fleſh is our Dalilah</note> is his own fleſh, and fleſhlie luſts, which are coupled nearer to him, than <hi>Dalilah</hi> was to <hi>Samſon;</hi> bred within vs, &amp; which we intertaine in our boſome; which carrie vs, or rather miſcarrie vs whitherſoeuer they pleaſe. The <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi>
                     <pb n="41" facs="tcp:2569:21"/>knewe what power <hi>Dalilah</hi> had ouer <hi>Samſon;</hi> and the Deuill knoweth how we are addicted to our own luſts; and therefore he chooſeth them as the fitteſt inſtruments to deceiue vs. <hi>Samſon</hi> ouercame the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and Luſt ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came him: <hi>Quem non vincit ferrum,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> 
                     <hi>vincit libido:</hi> Luſt ouercommeth him whom the Sworde could not ouercome. Therefore ſeeing Satan knoweth vs ſo well, and can find within our ſelues our owne <hi>Dalilah</hi> to deceiue vs, let vs take heed that our fleſhly luſts haue no commandement ouer vs, but that wee may leade them captiue, to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of Chriſt Ieſus.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>
                     <hi>The Argument which the Philiſtims</hi> vſe to make Dalilah to betray Samſon, is taken from commodity or gaine.</head>
                  <p>THe fiue Princes of the <hi>Philiſtims</hi> agree with <hi>Dalilah</hi> for each one eleuen hundreth ſhekles of Siluer,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 26.15.</note> which was a great price: &amp; both Chriſt and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> were ſolde for leſſer.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.28.</note> They knew what hope of gaine could work: for if it can blinde the eyes of the wiſe,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:2569:22"/>what will it not worke at the hands of an Harlot? for as Harlots are prodigall, ſo are they alſo auaritious, and make merchandize both of themſelues and of all others for gaine.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">An honeſt heart is not mercenarie. <hi>1,</hi> Tim. <hi>6.6</hi>
                     </note>A religious and honeſt heart is not mercenarie, neither can bee bought or ſolde; and it accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth godlineſſe to be great gaine: whereas a ſlauiſh &amp; earthly minded man accounteth gaine to bee godlineſſe, and will not ſticke to ſell Chriſt, his Religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, his King, his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, his Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience, his Soule, his friend, <hi>&amp; quid non?</hi> for Money.</p>
                  <p>This offer of the Princes of the <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtims</hi> imbraced by <hi>Dalilah,</hi> preſenteth vnto vs the price whereby the Deuill allureth our ſinfull nature to conſent vnto his temptations: for he knoweth what Gaine (and the offer of earthlie commodities) can doe at our hand. He will buy vs at a deare rate, to betray our true <hi>Samſon</hi> Chriſt Ieſus. He knew the couetous heart of <hi>Iudas,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.15.16.</note> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore preſented vnto him thirtie pieces of Money to betray his Maſter. But he knew that <hi>Peter</hi> nor <hi>Iohn</hi> could not bee
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:2569:22"/>ſeduced thereby. When <hi>Peter</hi> ſaid to <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Magus,</hi> (who offered him Money to ſell the gift of the holie Ghoſt) <hi>Let thy Money periſh with thy ſelf;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 8.20.</note> ſo they are not the ſucceſſors of <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Peter,</hi> (fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> whom the <hi>Roman</hi> church affirme to draw their diſcent,) but of <hi>Simo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Magus,</hi> who either buy or ſell holie thinges.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Samſons facilitie and ſecuritie.</head>
                  <p>SAMSON being ouercome of his luſts, yeeldeth ſo much to <hi>Dalilah,</hi> that after a threefold diſſimulation (wherby he would haue ſeemed to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt the temptations) he giues her three aduantages, and his diſſimulation ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth a doore to his defection;<note place="margin">Diſsimula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion a doore to defection</note> where if hee had reſiſted in the beginning, and altogether refuſed to ſhow her wherin his ſtrength laye, hee could not haue made ſuch Apoſtaſie, with the loſſe of the marks of his <hi>Nazareïſme</hi> &amp; religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</p>
                  <p>And this policie of <hi>Samſon,</hi> and diſſimulation, would ſeeme to be very plauſible to fleſh and blood, that wee ſhould put off time with our enemies,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:2569:23"/>and ſhoot off one ſhoure by keeping fayre wordes with them; thinking thereby that through tract of time they will bee ſlacker in their ſutes: by the contrarie it falleth out, that yeel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to them in one faire word, and going with them in the ſmalleſt thing, augmenteth their hop &amp; ſtirreth them vp to be more vehement, to be ſuting after farther: As if an houſe that were beſiedged would open the firſt entrie to the enemie,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> hee giueth him aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to perſue the reſt of the building more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Therefore let vs learne of the Apoſtle <hi>S. Iames</hi> to reſiſt the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uil,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames</hi> 4.7.</note> and he will flee from vs, and not to capitulate or parley with the Deuill in matters of faith and Religion, or to yeeld vnto him in the ſmalleſt thing; leſt hee ſute farther:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ex.</hi> 10.26.</note> but with <hi>Moſes,</hi> (when <hi>Pharaoh</hi> himſelfe ſought onlie the Sheepe of the <hi>Iſraelits</hi> to remaine in <hi>Egypt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Moſes hoofe.</note>) refuſe him any hoofe at all. So dangerous a thing it is to yeeld the ſmalleſt point or intch to anie perſon of the world in matters of Gods ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice: leſt by yeelding in one thing, at
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:2569:23"/>laſt wee bee brought to yeeld to all: as we ſee by the pittifull example of <hi>Sam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.</hi> And when the Deuill can obtaine thus much at our handes, that we may admit the badges or colours of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſt; yea, the ſmalleſt Ceremonie of that <hi>Romane</hi> Church; ſhall wee doubt that hee will ſtand there? no, but hee will ſeeke farther, and will not be ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied that we receiue his colours, vnleſſe we receiue himſelfe alſo, &amp; make ſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wracke of our conſciences, and denie the Faith. Like as a whoore-hunter ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding ſome of his rings, or other loue-tokens, to a young woman,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> if ſhee ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of them, hee perſwadeth himſelfe hee hath obtained her fauour: ſo if wee receiue the marks of Antichriſt, &amp; take vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs his colours, it ſhalbe ineuitable to refuſe himſelfe, but that we ſhal im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace that doctrine of deuils.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</note> Wherfore let vs reſiſt the beginning of euery euil. <hi>Samſon</hi> in his greateſt danger became ſecure,<note place="margin">Securitie.</note> &amp; fell aſleepe vpon the Harlots knee: and this deſigneth the fragility of mans nature: yea, the regenerate, that the wicked bee more vigilant to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:2569:24"/>their deuiliſh deuiſes, than the godlie bee to eſcape them. For yee ſee here <hi>Dalilah</hi> is waking, while <hi>Samſon</hi> is ſleeping:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 26.40.47.</note> ſo was <hi>Iudas,</hi> when the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles were faſt aſleepe in the Garden.</p>
                  <p>Next, the ſecuritie of <hi>Samſon</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenteth the dulneſſe of our nature,<note place="margin">Wee are moſt ſecure, when wee ſhould bee moſt vigi- Ionah <hi>1.5.</hi>
                     </note> that we are then moſt ſecure, when wee are in greateſt danger. So was <hi>Ionas</hi> in the ſhip, when the tempeſt of Gods wrath, &amp; the ſurges of the Sea were perſuing the ſhip, all were waking, onelie <hi>Ionas</hi> was aſleep, who ſhould haue bene moſt vigilant. And ſo is our Church this day, when Antichriſt, and all his confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derates and ſuppoſtes, are triumphing vpon the graues of Chriſtians, we are drinking in Bowles, &amp; making merrie with <hi>Beltaſchar.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.3.4.30.</note> But out of queſtion, God will waken vs, either in his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, or in his Iudgement, out of this dead-ſleepe, wherinto Princes, Paſtors, and people are lulled ouer at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent time.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>The Philistims are vpon thee Samſon.</head>
                  <p>THe Harlot hath two voyces: the firſt voyce when ſhee is tempting
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:2569:24"/>him to ſinne, <hi>If thou loue mee, thou wilt tell mee wherin thy great ſtrength ſtandeth.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Dalilah hath two voyces.</note> But when he hath yeelded, her ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d voyce is a voyce of deſtruction, <hi>The Philiſtims are vpon thee Samſon.</hi> So the Deuill hath two voyces to a ſinner: the one when hee is alluring &amp; perſwading vs to ſin, then hee ſeemeth to pretende loue and kindneſſe, &amp; promiſeth vs faire things: but when hee hath perſwaded vs to ſinne, then he terrifieth vs with his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond voyce, and ſaith, <hi>The Philistims are vpon thee Samſon, and the judgements of God.</hi> Firſt he lulleth vs aſleepe, with an hope of Gods mercies: but when hee hath ſnared vs, he proclaimeth warre, &amp; no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but Gods judgements. Therfore let vs beware to heare the whiſtling of the Serpent; leſt afterward wee heare the roaring of the Lyon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>SAMSONS WEAKNESSE.</head>
                  <p>HIs weakneſſe is deſcribed, that when his enemies came vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, he conceated with himſelf, that he had his former ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth: but in effect he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to bee as other men. Whereof wee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:2569:25"/>may learn two remarkable leſſons: firſt, that the ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth we haue is only of God;<note place="margin">The Lord our ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth.</note> &amp; once being left by him to our ſelues, we are a ready prey to our ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> if we caſt off our armour, we are naked before an armed man, &amp; our ſtrength is turned to weaknes: therfore let vs put on our armour, &amp; ſhake it not off. Next, we ſee the falſe confidence of fleſh and blood,<note place="margin">Falſe confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in our ſelues.</note> that wil aſcribe to it ſelfe ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, wiſdome, faith, &amp;c. when it hath nothing in it, but as it were one dreaming of victory in priſon.<note place="margin">Simil.</note> But whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                     <hi>Samſon</hi> commeth in his enemies hand, then he feeleth his owne weakenes, by dolefull experience. Let vs therfore not preſume of our giftes, leſt wee deceiue our ſelues in our imaginations, &amp; proue droſſe,<note place="margin">Simil.</note> where we ſuppoſed our ſelues to be gold: as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Spirit ſaies to the Church, <hi>Thou ſayeſt,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Apoc.</hi> 3.17</note> 
                     <hi>I am rich, and lacke nothing &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <head>Samſons fourefolde puniſhment.</head>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">God winkes not at ſinne.</note>NOw God juſtly chaſtiſes his own ſeruant, with foure rods; to let vs ſee, that the Lord wil not winke at the faultes of his Elect: albeit hee will not take his holy Spirit fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> them, as he did
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:2569:25"/>fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe of <hi>Saul;</hi> but chaſtiſe them with the rod of his children, and viſite them with his temporall corrections, that they might eſcape eternall judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. So did hee to <hi>Dauid,</hi> and the reſt of his Saincts; and ſo wil he ſtill doe to his choſen children for euermore.</p>
                  <p>Now the firſt puniſhment which the Lord layeth on <hi>Samſon,</hi> is BLINDNES.<note place="margin">Samſons firſt pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.21.</note> And it is the juſt recompence of God, that wherein man ſinneth, therin he is puniſhed. <hi>Samſons</hi> eyes were full of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes, &amp; they were pulled out of his head.<note place="margin">Wherin we ſinne, therin ſhall we be puniſhed.</note> Our eyes are apointed for better vſes, to wit, that we may beholde Gods workes, and glorifie him therein. But when they are inſtruments of wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, &amp; through which windowes we ſend foorth the vncleane luſts of a pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted heart, and open them to admit &amp; giue entry to wicked allurementes of others; then no doubt God may juſtlie puniſh thoſe members which ſinned. We haue an exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of <hi>Adonebezek,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.7.</note> king of <hi>Bezek,</hi> who cut off the thombs and toes of LXX. kings, whom he bound in chains vnder his table, and ſaith, <hi>As I
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:2569:26"/>haue done to others, God hath done to me.</hi> The <hi>Allegorie</hi> holds wel of our ſpiritual ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, who when they layhold on vs, &amp; get vs firſt into their handes, they pull our eyes, that we neither ſee God, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, hell, nor our ſelues. But as the Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen firſt plucketh out the eyes of the Lambe,<note place="margin">Simil. Satan firſt blindeth vs, and then killeth vs. Iſa. <hi>6.9.</hi>
                     </note> &amp; then deuours the reſt of the fleſh; ſo doeth Satan firſt blind vs, and then kill vs. When God threatned a judgement vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his people, by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, he ſaid he <hi>would ſmite them with a blindnes, yea, a double blindnes, that they ſhal haue eyes, and not perceiue;</hi> ſurely progno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticating their temporall deſtruction. This blindnes befell the men of <hi>Sodome</hi> before the fire:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 19.11 <hi>Numb.</hi> 22.23.</note> and to <hi>Balaam</hi> (that hee ſaw not the Angel) before the Sword: and to the <hi>Aramites,</hi> before they came to <hi>Samaria.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 18 6</note> But <hi>David,</hi> the ſeruant of God, ſaw the Angel with a drawn ſword, &amp; humbled himſelfe before the Lord.<note place="margin">2. <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17.</note> Therefore let vs ſtudie to vſe the light which we haue, rightlie, that it bee not turned into darknes: for <hi>if the light that is in vs be darknes, how great ſhal this darknes be?</hi> But to apply this doctrine, they are more than blinde who ſee not a
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:2569:26"/>double blindnes ſeazed vpon vs, and both our eyes to bee blind-folded:<note place="margin">Double blindneſſe.</note> for we ſee pleaſures, honours, and wealth, as the great Courteour ſawe after the ſiedge of <hi>Samaria,</hi> though hee neuer ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted therof.<note place="margin">2. <hi>King.</hi> 7.20.</note> Let vs dreame to our ſelues by offending our God to purchaſe ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours and wealth, but in the morning our hand ſhalbe emptie. Next, we are blind in this,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 5.2.</note> that we ſee not the flying booke of <hi>Zacharias,</hi> of XX. cubits long, and X. cubits broade, bringing woe to the inhabitants of this miſerable Land, for Blaſphemie, Sacriledge, Idolatrie, Perjurie, Witch-craft, Adulterie, and Drunkenneſſe, beſides innumerable other vices, wherewith this Land is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed. The Lord open our eyes, that we may ſee our ſinnes, and beholde thoſe letters which are written on the wall, at which <hi>Beltaſchar</hi> trembled:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 5.5.</note> that the ſcales falling down from our eyes, wee may repent, amend, and be ſaued.<note place="margin">Samſons ſecond puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.21.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Samſons</hi> ſecond puniſhment, is HIS BANDS. By which yee ſee howe ſinne ſpoyleth &amp; robbeth men of libertie, &amp; bringeth them to captiuitie &amp; ſlauerie:
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:2569:27"/>for there is nothing which al creatures wiſh more after,<note place="margin">Sinne ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth free men ſlaues.</note> than Libertie, (ſo that the Poet called Libertie, <hi>The beſt of all things:</hi>) and that Nature abhors nothing more than Bondage. Yet ſinne makes a man a ſlaue, and depriues him of that liberty which God &amp; Nature gaue him. Sinne bound the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> in <hi>Aegypt</hi> and <hi>Babylon:</hi> and I greatly feare, that our ſinnes alſo bring vs vnder ſlauery both of body and conſcience, becauſe wee abuſe the liberty which we haue vnder our gracious Prince. Wee may ſee what it is to abuſe the liberty that God giueth vs: for it prouoketh him to caſt bondes on vs: as Chriſt ſaide to <hi>Peter, When thou waſt young,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob.</hi> 21.18.</note> 
                     <hi>thou walked whither thou wouldeſt: but whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thou art old, thou ſhalt be caried by others.</hi> For vnto <hi>Samſons</hi> miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is added the third afflictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for being caſten as a ſlaue into priſon, he is forced to grind to the <hi>Philiſtims.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">The abuſe of Gods pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience brin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction.</note> Becauſe in his libertie he would not ſerue God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in his captiuitie hee muſt ſerue his enemies: ſo the Lord is forced to vſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremities, and to deale ſharply with his beſt children, if they abuſe his patience by the lice<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiouſnes of their corrupt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:2569:27"/>Then ye may ſee, by the bonds and impriſonment of <hi>Samſon,</hi> what are the rewardes and recompenſes of the fleſh, &amp; of ſuch as follow Harlots: they are caried as an Oxe to the ſlaughter,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Prov.</hi> 7.22.</note> &amp; as fools to the ſtocks for correctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: for God hath many bondes and priſons, wherein he can faſten our feet: bondes of yron, and of ſicknes, tying vs to our beds: he hath priſon-houſes &amp; wardes to keep vs faſt:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.20.</note> he bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d <hi>Nabuchadnezar</hi> with chains of yron: he bound <hi>Adonebe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zek</hi> vnder the table, and <hi>Zedekiah,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 1.7. 2. <hi>King.</hi> 25.7.</note> king of <hi>Iudah,</hi> was caried bound to <hi>Babel,</hi> and caſt into priſon. And haue we not ſeene with our eyes, heard with our cares, &amp; read in hiſtories, that the priſon-houſes haue beene ſo pleniſhed with Noble Perſons, Princes, Earles, and lordes, (I omit Gentlemen &amp; other Commons, becauſe it is ſo vſuall) that they could ſcarce containe them? If ye inquire the cauſe why they are caſten into bonds: it is anſwered, <hi>For debt.</hi> And next, if it be asked, how did they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tract that debt, and ſpend their reuenues? was it vpon the honourable affairs of their country
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:2569:28"/>and king? was it for the prouiſion of their children, to beſtow them honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rably in marriage, or ſuch like? It is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, <hi>No forſooth.</hi> Then it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded thirdly, What it can bee that hath brought ſo great Men to ſtrait wardes? And then it is replied, <hi>He was take in the priſon of a whoores chamber, and ſhee by her prodigall maintenance hath brought him to this priſon.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Whoores bring men to Priſon.</note> So <hi>Samſon</hi> being firſt caught with <hi>Dalilah,</hi> is afterwardes conuoyed to the priſon of the <hi>Philiſtims,</hi> and conſtrained to grind in their Milns. But let vs ſarre rather bind &amp; impriſon them firſt, that they bind not vs. Better ſlay them, than they vs. But would to God that theſe externall cordes, bondes of yron, and priſons of ſtone,<note place="margin">Man is bound with his owne ſinnes. Iude verſ. <hi>6</hi> Matth. <hi>22 13</hi>
                     </note> were the worſt. But the eternall God will lay hand vpon that wicked and prophane man, and bind him hands &amp; feet, with the bonds of his owne ſinne, (which are ſpiritual bondes) and caſt him into euerlaſting chaines, vnder darknes, to bee reſerued to the laſt day; deliuering him to the lailor, and the lailor ſhall caſt him into vtter darknes:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eſay</hi> 30.33</note> into <hi>Topheth,</hi> which is prepared for the king: the fire whereof
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:2569:28"/>is kindled by the breath of Gods own noſtrels, as a riuer of brimſtone:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Zach.</hi> 9.11</note> which is a pit without water, and the priſon of which <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4. <hi>and</hi> 3.19.</note> whereinto the Angels were caſten, and deliuered into chains of darknes, to bee kept in dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. If ye therefore be not afraide of theſe earthlie priſons, into the which no doubt your ſinne will bring you, if ye doe not repent in time, and namelie thoſe ſinnes of adultery &amp; whoordom; yet feare the eternal chains and priſon, whoſe doors ſhall neuer open,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> neither is there any means to eſcape them; but yee ſhalbe ſure to lie there perpetually, tormented with the Deuill and his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels. Iudge yee then, I pray you, if yee haue not bought ſo ſhort a pleaſure at a deare rate,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Samſons third pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment.</hi> Iudg. <hi>16.21.</hi> The abuſe of libertie brings men to ſlauerie. Ier. <hi>2.24.</hi>
                     </note> which will coſt you euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting paines.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Samſons</hi> third puniſhment is, that <hi>bee muſt grind in the Milne.</hi> Which letteth vs ſee yet farther how that the abuſe of li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty bringeth vs to ſlauery. When we are young in ſinne, wee goe where wee will, euen with the wilde Aſſe, till our moneth come, when we ſhall be taken.
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:2569:29"/>The <hi>Iſraelites</hi> abuſing their libertie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came ſlaues to the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 1.14 <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.24 1. <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.12.</note> and made Bricke to <hi>Pharoah.</hi> They became tribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries to <hi>Caeſar. Saul</hi> tooke their daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters to be waſhers, and their ſonnes to run after his Chariots. Let vs take heed then, euen by the example of others, that wobecome not ſlaues to ſinne and our owne corruptions, leſt ſinne make vs ſlaues to men, and their affections. Let vs grinde no longer to the Deuill, leſt hee cauſe vs to grinde to our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall enemies here, and in hell for euer. He will put vs to the Galleyes, &amp; binde vs to row in chains: he will caſt vs vnder his table, as a dog, with <hi>Ado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nebezek,</hi> when hee hath cut off our right thombs and toes. Therfore let vs reſiſt Satan in time, and all our filthie luſts, that we be not brought into per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall ſlauerie both of body and ſoule.</p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Samfons fourth puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.25.</note>Now <hi>Samſons</hi> fourth puniſhment is OPEN SHAME: wherein wee may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue the juſt recompenſe of <hi>Samſon</hi> in euery thing: his luſtfull eyes are pulled out: the abuſe of his liberty is turned to bonds: his ſlauery to ſinne, is turned to the ſlauery of his fleſh: &amp; now laſt, his
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:2569:29"/>diſhonour to God,<note place="margin">God recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſeth Samſon juſtly in all his puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>2.</hi> Sam. <hi>12.14.</hi>
                     </note> turneth to his open ſhame. For as the Lord will honour them who honour him; ſo hee will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour them who diſhonour his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Name. <hi>Samſon</hi> made Gods Name to be euil ſpeke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of (as <hi>Dauid</hi> did) before the <hi>Heathen,</hi> &amp; ſlandered his profeſſion: now he is made a publike ſpectacle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the eyes of Gods enemies. Let no man think thoſe pure in their profeſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that cry, <hi>The Temple of the Lord,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ier.</hi> 7.4.</note> 
                     <hi>the te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple of the Lord,</hi> if they denle their body, which is the true Temple of God. Fie, and fie again, vpon the ſwiniſh life of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors of the Euangel of Chriſt: for the <hi>Ethniks</hi> (who made more conſcience in their honeſt behauiour) <hi>Turks, Iewes</hi> and <hi>Papiſts,</hi> ſhal condemne them: and it ſhal bee eaſier for them at the Great Day, than to ſuch who brag of their puritie in religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; yet they liue in a ſhameles impuritie of life: witneſſing to all the worlde,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Titus</hi> 1.16.</note> that they confeſſe Chriſt with their mouth, and denie him in their workes: ſhewing themſelues to be hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites, prepared for vtter darkneſſe.</p>
                  <p>But let no man miſconſtruct the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:2569:30"/>of God, as though hee had caſten off thoſe whom he brings to be publik examples to the world vpon open ſcaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>folds, or ſuch like. For God therby will proclaim that he will not countenance thoſe ſinnes in his children,<note place="margin">God puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth the ſinnes of his owne children here more rigorouſlie than hee doeth the wickeds. <hi>1.</hi> Cor. <hi>4.9.</hi>
                     </note> which hee will puniſh in the reprobate; albeit hee chaſtiſe the one, while hee plague the other. Yea, I reade in all the Scriptures, that externallie God dealeth more ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorouſlie with his own, than with his aduerſaries. Chriſt was made a publike ſpectacle to the world: and <hi>Paul</hi> ſaieth, <hi>Wee are made a publike gazing ſtocke to man and Angels:</hi> but we differ, in that wee are made ſpectacles for our own ſinnes, &amp; hee was made a ſpectacle for vs. And if it pleaſe God to bring vs to bee open martyrs, &amp; ſo ſpectacles to the world, let vs ſee it bee for the Lordes cauſe, as <hi>Samſon</hi> did: for <hi>Cauſa, non mors, facit marty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem,</hi> the cauſe, not the death, maketh a martyr. Here is the goodnes of God, that he might haue puniſhed <hi>Samſon</hi> by this ſhame for his ſinne,<note place="margin">Nota.</note> and yet he tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth it vnto his owne glorie, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth him ſuffer for his cauſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="subpart">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:2569:30"/>
                  <head>Samſons Triumph.</head>
                  <p>IT is true which is ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Weeping may be at euening,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 30.5.</note> 
                     <hi>but joye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in the morning:</hi> and that which our Sauiour ſaieth,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matt.</hi> 5.4.</note> 
                     <hi>Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall receiue conſolation:</hi> for this Tragoedie of <hi>Samſons</hi> life endeth with a joyfull plauditie, with the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie of the Church from her enemies, and his owne deliuerie from ſinne and ſhame. But firſt let vs obſerue,<note place="margin">Mans greateſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitie is Gods chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt oportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie.</note> that when <hi>Samſon</hi> is fartheſt dejected and brought to the laſt and greateſt point of diſgrace, then the Lord commeth: and it is his proper time when hee worketh, which is contrary to the doeings of men: for when wee ſee anie exalted to the toppe of their honour, then all men bow their knee to <hi>Haman:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Heſter</hi> 3.2 <hi>and</hi> 5.14 <hi>&amp;</hi> 6.1. <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </note> but when the Gallows is ſet vp for <hi>Mordicai,</hi> &amp; ſentence giuen out againſt the <hi>Iewes,</hi> then commeth the Saluation of God: for when <hi>Ionas</hi> ſaid,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ionas</hi> 2.4.</note> 
                     <hi>I am caſt out of thy ſight,</hi> then his eyes were to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward his holy place. The neceſſitie of <hi>Iob</hi> was the oportunitie of God:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iob</hi> 42.10</note> for being depriued of al worldly comfort,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:2569:31"/>his wife, children, friends, ſeruants, &amp;c. and all had forſaken him, then the Lord commeth, and reſtoreth him to all things. <hi>David</hi> found this ſame proof, and all the Saincts in all ages, that in their greateſt extremities his ſtrength may be manifeſted to the world, to the glorie of his grace, that fleſh &amp; blood ſhould haue no place of rejoycing in it ſelfe, but giue all glorie to God; <hi>All men forſooke me,</hi> ſayeth the Apoſtle,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.16.17. <hi>Iob.</hi> 9.35.</note> 
                     <hi>But the Lord aſsiſted me.</hi> As the borne blind being caſten foorth of the Synagogue by the <hi>Phariſies,</hi> vvas found by Chriſt, ſo vvhen vvee are rejected by the vvorld, the Lord ſhall find vs. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let this encourage the Church of God at all times, and all her members; that howſoeuer the Ship of Ieſus bee toſſed vvith vvaues all the night,
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.24.25.</note> yet in the fourth vvatch the Lord vvill come, and rebuke the vvind and the vvaues, and make calme the tempeſts of the Seas, and bring peace to <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Next, vve ſee that vvhen the enemies of the Church cry peace, then co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth their ſudden deſtructio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. The <hi>Philiſtims</hi> are triumphing ouer <hi>Samſon,</hi> &amp; reuiling
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:2569:31"/>his God, and praiſing their god <hi>Dag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iudg.</hi> 16.24.</note> that dead monſter: and in the meane time God bringeth ſudden deſtruction vpon them. <note place="margin">When the wicked are moſt ſecure. then com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction. Matth. <hi>24.38.</hi>
                     </note> As in the firſt vvorld they vvere eating, and drinking; marrying, and giuing in marriage; and the flood came: So vvhen the enemies of the Church are in their greateſt joy, then they are ſinging (vvith the Svvan) their ovvne funerall ſong. Thirdlie, vve muſt obſerue that God reſtoreth ſtrength to <hi>Samſon,</hi> vvhich he had loſt by his ovvne follie: <note place="margin">As God ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteth down, ſo in his owne time he raiſeth vp againe.</note> vvherein the conſtancie of God is to bee ſeene; that vvhom God loueth, he loueth to the ende. <hi>Samſons</hi> fooliſhneſſe could not prejudge Gods goodneſſe. So it is certaine, that albeit the Lord vvil hide himſelfe a little from his Sainctes, and abſtract his ſpirituall giftes from them for a ſeaſon, aſwell to their owne ſence &amp; feeling, as to the ſight of the world;
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Numb.</hi> 23.19.</note> yet it is impoſſible that God can repent as man, or change his nature, who is immutable, &amp; with him (as th' Apoſtle ſaith) there is no ſhaddow of changing. <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iames</hi> 1.17</note> Then let vs take heart, euen when wee ſeeme to bee fartheſt caſten down, and
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:2569:32"/>that the graces of God are dried vp vpon vs. For the Lord will alwayes be like himſelfe, and immutable. And this is alſo remarkable, that whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the inward graces are reſtored to the ſoule, <note place="margin">Simil.</note> hee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couereth alſo the ſtrength of his body: for as it is in corporal diſeaſes, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the noble affected parts are cured and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, then the exterior partes of the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die begin to conualeſſe: That ſame or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der God keepeth in our ſpirituall cure, ſaying firſt, <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mat.</hi> 9.2.5</note> 
                     <hi>Thy ſinnes are forgiuen thee:</hi> and then, <hi>Take vp thy Bed, and walke. Dauid</hi> felt the proofe hereof, when he confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his ſinnes, and ſaith, <hi>And thou tookest away the puniſhment of my ſinnes.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſa. <hi>32.50</hi> If wee firſt ſeeke ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicke, then wee ſhall find eaſe in our tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles.</note> So let vs labour in all our extremities to ſeeke firſt ſpirituall phyſicke, and reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with our God: and then if it pleaſe him, hee will ſoone eaſe vs of our tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall troubles. Farther, let vs obſerue that the external ſeale of his graces and marke of his <hi>Nazareiſme,</hi> which was in <hi>Samſons</hi> haire, is alſo reſtored to him before his death. So that in whatſoeuer thing ſinne had made him deficient, now grace makes him ſufficient. <note place="margin">What ſinne maketh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient in vs, grace maketh ſufficient.</note> So the preſence of God by his grace is able to
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:2569:32"/>ſupplie all our wantes, and loſſes. As for the pulling down of the houſe, It may bee thought that <hi>Samſon</hi> deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratelie ouerthroweth himſelfe, with the <hi>Philiſtims:</hi> but it carrieth no reaſon with it: for firſt he is reckoned (<hi>Heb.</hi> 11.32.) in the catalogue of the faithfull captains of <hi>Iſrael,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Whether Samſo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> died desperatelie or not.</note> who by ſaith wroght righteouſneſſe, and ouercame King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes: which the Spirit of God would not had done, if hee had died deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratelie. Next, God had not reſtored vnto him his graces after his fall, but onlie to vſe them to his glorie. Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, <hi>Samſon</hi> intended nothing but the deſtruction of Gods enemies, albeit with his own loſſe, whereto he offered himſelfe willingly, being a Magiſtrate, and hauing power to giue his life for the Saluation of the people. The an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient <hi>Romans</hi> thought it a great honour, <hi>Mori pro Patria,</hi> to die for their contrey, as <hi>Samſon</hi> doeth here. <note place="margin">Samſon a type of Chriſt.</note> 
                     <hi>Samſon</hi> was a figure of Chriſt, who in his life killed many of our Spirituall enemies; but in his death hee pulled downe the pillars of Satans Kingdome, and ouercame ſinne, Hell, and death, that wee may
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:2569:33"/>cry nowe, <hi>O death, where is thy ſting? O Hell,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55.</note> 
                     <hi>where is thy victorie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">The appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of theſe ſeuen Lockes.</note>Nowe yee haue heard the ſeuen Lockes of <hi>Samſon</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="4 letters">
                        <desc>••••</desc>
                     </gap>gorically the ſeuenfold grac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> of Gods Spir<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> beſtowed vpon his children: which ſeuen Locks, as marks of Chriſtianitie, we ſhold try if we haue them growing in our hearts. Next, we ſhould learn a caueat by <hi>Samſons</hi> ſecuritie &amp; facilitie. leſt wee giue place to the Deuill, and leſt hee ſpoyle vs of our Spirituall gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. Thirdlie, by his puniſhments let vs remember that God will not ſpare his deareſt children, if they diſho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour his Name. And finallie, by his recouerie wee haue to praiſe the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of God, who mixeth his mercies with his Iuſtice, and forgetteth the ſinnes of the elect, and crowneth them with compaſſions, to his euerlaſting glorie: to whom be praiſe and honour for euer and euer. Amen.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2569:33"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
